<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-09T13:12:09+00:00</updated><id>https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog.xml</id><title type="html">Collective Futurecrafting</title><subtitle>Collective Futurecrafting is a wholistic system for place based and community-led transformation, weaving ancient wisdom with modern innovation to create flourishing futures for all life.</subtitle><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><entry><title type="html">A Living Story of Adapting Communities to Thrive: Join in on the ACT</title><link href="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/03/06/a-living-story-of-adapting-communities-to-thrive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Living Story of Adapting Communities to Thrive: Join in on the ACT" /><published>2025-03-06T01:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-06T01:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/03/06/a-living-story-of-adapting-communities-to-thrive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/03/06/a-living-story-of-adapting-communities-to-thrive/"><![CDATA[<p>Like rain pooling on parched earth, slowly finding channels to flow together into streams, then rivers, so too do our collective responses to climate challenges begin as scattered actions, gradually connecting into powerful currents of change.</p>

<p>This is the essence of <strong>Adapting Communities to Thrive (ACT)</strong>. Co-creating a living, participatory journey where our diverse knowledge, experiences, and visions converge to map adaptation pathways. And today, we’re opening a new channel for this convergence: <strong>the ACT Mural</strong>.</p>

<p>This digital canvas can become a living map of our collective intelligence, a space where the wisdom of many Earthians can mingle and multiply, revealing patterns that none of us could see alone.</p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-sky-terra
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/horizons/3-deep-horizons.png')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
  <h2>Weaving wisdom across communities</h2>
  <p>The challenges we face are too complex for isolated solutions. No single perspective or expertise will be enough.</p>
  <p>Instead, we need to weave together diverse knowledge, experiences, and creativity from the head, heart and hands of our communities.</p>
  
    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<h2 id="why-a-mural-for-adaptation">Why a Mural for Adaptation?</h2>

<p>The scale and complexity of climate adaptation requires a new form of collaborative intelligence. A form that can honor local knowledge while enabling shared learning across communities. One that inspire us to imagine and co-create a future where we can thrive.</p>

<p>The ACT Mural offers a space where:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Local wisdom becomes visible</strong> alongside scientific insights</li>
  <li><strong>Emerging experiments</strong> can be connected to reveal patterns</li>
  <li><strong>Future visions</strong> can be co-created across different perspectives</li>
  <li><strong>Your voice</strong> joins a growing tapestry of community adaptation strategies</li>
</ul>

<p>This isn’t just another online whiteboard, it’s living map of collective intelligence that feeds directly into the upcoming ACT events and beyond, helping to shape tangible action and policy.</p>

<h2 id="exploring-the-three-horizons">Exploring the Three Horizons</h2>

<p>The Mural is structured around the <strong>Three Horizons framework</strong>: a powerful way to imagine and navigate transformation.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Horizon 1: Business-as-Usual &amp; Current Challenges</strong>: What’s holding us back? What challenges do you see in your community? What are people saying—or not saying—about climate change?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Horizon 2: The Transition Zone</strong>: How might we adapt together? What seeds are you planting, both literal and metaphorical? What emerging experiments inspire you? How might we build bridges between composting the old and crafting the new?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Horizon 3: The Future of Thriving Communities</strong>: Imagine writing letters from 2035. What does an adapted, thriving community look and feel like? What do you see, hear, smell, and feel in this flourishing future?</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Each horizon needs your caring contribution, and you can move freely between them as you explore different perspectives.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/posts/three-horizons-h3uni-image.jpg" alt="Three Horizons framework visualization showing the transition between present challenges, emerging possibilities, and future visions" class="blog-image" />
  <figcaption>The Three Horizons framework helps us navigate the space between present challenges, emerging possibilities, and future visions. Image from <a href="https://www.h3uni.org/" target="_blank">H3Uni</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Like the <span class="footnote-ref">mycelial networks<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup><span class="footnote-tooltip">Mycelial networks are the underground systems of fungi that connect trees and plants in forests, sharing nutrients and information across ecosystems. A beautiful metaphor for how our collective knowledge can spread and nourish communities and our planet we are part of.</span></span> beneath forest floors that connect trees in vast communication webs, the Mural creates connections between ideas, projects, and possibilities that might otherwise remain isolated. Through these connections, something greater than the sum of parts begins to emerge.</p>

<h2 id="how-best-to-engage-with-the-mural">How best to engage with the Mural</h2>

<p>Ready to join this collaborative space? Here’s how to make the most of it:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Set aside 20-30 minutes</strong> for thoughtful engagement (the Mural works best on desktop browsers)</li>
  <li><strong>Start in the sandbox</strong> if this is your first time using Mural, learn how to create sticky notes, add images, and explore the basic tools</li>
  <li><strong>Check out the “How &amp; What to Contribute” section</strong> for ideas on different ways to participate</li>
  <li><strong>Get inspired by community initiatives</strong> by exploring the video case studies of climate adaptation projects across NSW</li>
  <li><strong>Choose which horizon you want to explore first</strong> and add your voice through:
    <ul>
      <li>Sticky notes sharing your experiences, worries, or hopes</li>
      <li>Images from your community showing adaptation in action</li>
      <li>Poems or stories about adaptation journeys</li>
      <li>Letters from the future imagining thriving communities</li>
      <li>Links to projects that inspire you</li>
      <li>Questions that need exploring</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Remember, this isn’t about having perfect ideas or polished contributions. It’s about bringing your authentic perspective into a growing collective intelligence. The Mural is a conversational place to both share and be inspired by others.</p>

<h2 id="what-happens-next">What happens next?</h2>

<p>The Mural isn’t a static exercise. It’s a living process and just one part of the broader ACT journey. As patterns emerge, connections form, and insights arise, we’ll be:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hosting some online workshops with work through the ACT Mural experience together. <a href="https://tally.so/r/wkvNv1" target="_blank">Register your interest here</a> to be notified about upcoming sessions.</li>
  <li>Weaving your contributions into futher stories and imagination exercises to share back with the larger community.</li>
  <li>Bringing community stories, voices and wisdom into the <strong>AdaptNSW Forum</strong></li>
  <li>Creating a <strong>visual archive of community wisdom</strong> that continues to evolve</li>
  <li>Identifying opportunities for <strong>collaborative action</strong> across communities</li>
</ul>

<p>Your contributions become part of a growing body of knowledge about how we might adapt and thrive together. This participatory approach reflects a core insight: adaptation isn’t something done <em>to</em> communities, but <em>by</em> communities, drawing on their inherent wisdom and creativity.</p>

<p><em>Note: The Mural is a public space, and your contributions will be visible to others. Please be aware of your own privacy and that of others you may share stories about, and only share content that you are comfortable with being public.</em></p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/posts/enter-as-ACT-as-visitor.jpg" alt="Image of the Mural with instruction explaining to enter as a visitor" class="blog-image" />
</figure>
<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/posts/ACT-Mural-Outline.jpg" alt="Image of the Mural with instruction pointing how to start with the outline" class="blog-image" />
</figure>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-sky-terra
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--full
  parallax-section--padding-medium" style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/posts/ACT-Mural-parallax.png')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>ACT with us</h2>
<p>
  We need your voice, your stories, your wisdom, your heart, your dreams. Just enter the Mural as a visitor and add your voice to the collective canvas.
</p>
<a href="https://app.mural.co/t/greaterthanexperience9110/m/greaterthanexperience9110/1740178225790/047b29a8f3ccaa94f770be062905b54e7ce2261e?sender=ubc2338b15fb7ad7803547648" target="_blank" class="button button--primary">Enter as a visitor</a>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<h2 id="the-broader-the-act-journey">The broader the ACT journey</h2>

<p>The Mural is one piece of a larger journey of collective futurecrafting with the AdaptNSW community. Here are a few ways to get involved…</p>

<p><strong>Join the Pol.is</strong> <a href="https://pol.is/2iyhcxfjkr" target="_blank"><strong>conversation here</strong></a> and share your perspective on what becomes possible when we weave together the transformative power of community-led adaptation</p>

<p><strong>Attend the AdaptNSW ACT event!</strong> <a href="https://events.humanitix.com/adapting-communities-to-thrive" target="_blank"> Get your free tickets</a> and experience emerging insights through film, art and dialogue at our family-friendly evening on Friday, March 14th for Climate Action Week</p>

<p><a href="https://www.climatechange.environment.nsw.gov.au/home" target="_blank"> Explore the AdaptNSW website</a> and connect with broader adaptation initiatives and trusted, localised climate information</p>

<p><strong>Invite others</strong> - Share the this article with friends, family, or neighbours who might want to contribute their ideas about transformative climate adaptation and community thriving</p>

<div class="quote-callout 
  quote-callout--theme-terra-sky
  quote-callout--large
  quote-callout--center">
  <div class="quote-callout__content">
    <blockquote class="quote-callout__quote">
      What we practice at the small scale sets the patterns for the whole system
    </blockquote>
    
      <cite class="quote-callout__attribution">Adrienne Maree Brown</cite>
    
  </div>
</div>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Mycelial networks are the underground systems of fungi that connect trees and plants in forests, sharing nutrients and information across ecosystems. They offer a powerful metaphor for how our collective knowledge can spread and nourish communities. For more, see <a href="https://www.suzannesimard.com/finding-the-mother-tree" target="_blank">Suzanne Simard’s work</a> on forest communication. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><category term="Climate Adaptation" /><category term="community wisdom" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Like rain pooling on parched earth, slowly finding channels to flow together into streams, then rivers, so too do our collective responses to climate challenges begin as scattered actions, gradually connecting into powerful currents of change.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/ACT-journey.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/ACT-journey.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Garden of Relational Capital</title><link href="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/02/28/garden-of-relational-capitalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Garden of Relational Capital" /><published>2025-02-28T01:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-28T01:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/02/28/garden-of-relational-capitalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/02/28/garden-of-relational-capitalism/"><![CDATA[<p>Our current financial system, fixated on short-term gains, fuels environmental harm, social strife, and economic volatility. But what if there was another way? What if we could cultivate an economic system that treats the well-being of individuals, communities, and the planet as the true currency?</p>

<p>This is the promise of relational capital—an alternative that composts exploitative models, opting instead for self-organising systems around kinship with life where everyone can flourish.</p>

<h2 id="the-story-of-a-community-garden">The story of a community garden</h2>

<p>Imagine a community garden in a struggling town. A small group of neighbours secures a modest grant to buy seeds and tools. Excitement builds as people volunteer their time, clearing land, planting seeds, and sharing meals together. The garden becomes a hub of activity, fostering friendships and community pride. More people join, and the garden grows.</p>

<p><strong>But what made the garden thrive in those early days? Was it just the money, or something deeper?</strong></p>

<p>When the grant eventually runs out, the garden faces a crisis. Without funds, some volunteers drop out, some of the committed members feel disheartened, and the plants begin to wither. The remaining members gather to brainstorm solutions. One neighbour suggests hosting a seed exchange with nearby towns, another proposes a “garden-as-classroom” for local children.</p>

<p>In this moment of challenge, they realise the garden’s true value isn’t in the grant but in the relationships and shared purpose it created.</p>

<p><strong>How did the garden survive when the money ran out? What role did trust, creativity, and shared goals play?</strong></p>

<p>The garden reinvents itself as a relational hub. Neighbours begin trading surplus produce, teaching each other composting techniques, and hosting events for local artists. The project scales organically—local schools adopt “garden days,” nearby cafes source herbs from the garden, and the town becomes known for its collaborative spirit. Once a small niche of land, has become a thriving ecosystem of relationships.</p>

<p><strong>What changed? How did focusing on relationships and shared purpose create lasting impact, even without financial capital?</strong></p>

<h2 id="from-transactional-to-relational-economics">From transactional to relational economics</h2>

<p>Traditional economic models rely on financial capital to activate ideas. But when money dries up, momentum often dies with it. A relational economy flips this script:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Value comes from trust, creativity, and shared purpose</li>
  <li>Success is measured by resilience, not just revenue</li>
  <li>Growth happens through collaboration, not competition</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>What if every initiative started with building relationships instead of focusing on financial capital raising? How might that change education, healthcare, or environmental action?</strong></p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-olive-gold
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/seed-of-life-hero-rough.svg')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>Information, Connection, and Wisdom</h2>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<h2 id="the-gardens-deeper-wisdom">The garden’s deeper wisdom</h2>

<p>As the garden thrives, the neighbours notice something unexpected. The plants seem to communicate—strawberries signal soil health to tomatoes, bees navigate via unseen patterns, and the garden’s layout begins to mirror the town’s fractal-like river system.</p>

<p>A local elder shares stories of First Peoples’ land practices, where circles and spirals align with Earth’s rhythms. The garden, it seems, is not just a plot of land but a living network.</p>

<p><strong>What if the garden’s success isn’t random? What if it’s a reflection of deeper laws—like how First Peoples see land as a living entity, or how quantum physics shows particles are interconnected?</strong></p>

<h3 id="information-as-lifeblood">Information as lifeblood</h3>

<p>In the garden, data (soil pH) becomes wisdom (sustainable practices) through relationships:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Data</strong>: Raw measurements (soil composition, rainfall)</li>
  <li><strong>Information</strong>: Data with context (“This soil thrives with rainwater”)</li>
  <li><strong>Knowledge</strong>: Shared techniques (composting methods)</li>
  <li><strong>Wisdom</strong>: Purpose-driven questions (“How does this garden heal our town?”)</li>
</ul>

<p>This mirrors the DIKW hierarchy—data → information → knowledge → wisdom—showing how value emerges from connection.</p>

<h3 id="fractal-patterns-of-change">Fractal patterns of change</h3>

<p>A schoolchild draws the garden’s layout, noticing it resembles a Mandelbrot set—a fractal pattern found in galaxies and snowflakes. The community realises their efforts mirror cosmic laws: small, organised actions (planting seeds) create large-scale harmony (a thriving ecosystem).</p>

<p><strong>What if our choices are like fractal patterns? Small acts of kindness, creativity, or care—could they ripple into global change?</strong></p>

<h3 id="quantum-connections">Quantum connections</h3>

<p>A local scientist explains how plants use quantum effects to photosynthesize, and how mycorrhizal fungi networks share nutrients like an internet. The garden, it turns out, is a quantum symphony of relationships, not just a collection of plants.</p>

<p><strong>If particles are entangled, and ecosystems are networks, what does that say about us? Are we separate, or part of a larger consciousness?</strong></p>

<h2 id="relational-reality-and-first-peoples-wisdom">Relational reality and First People’s wisdom</h2>

<p>The garden’s fractal patterns echo First Peoples land practices, where circles and spirals align with Earth’s rhythms. This suggests a universal logic where small actions (local gardens) reflect cosmic order.</p>

<p>Scientific discoveries (quantum photosynthesis, fungal networks) reveal that life thrives on relationships, not just resources. This challenges the “separate parts” view of traditional economics, aligning with the garden’s story of interdependence.</p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-terra-sky
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/horizons/3-deep-horizons.png')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>How we see ourselves in the world shapes how we act in it.</h2>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why this matters</h2>

<p>The garden’s journey shows that value isn’t just in capital or data—it’s in relationships. When we see life as a living network, not a machine:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Problems become opportunities for creativity</li>
  <li>Failure is a patterned lesson, not an end</li>
  <li>Success is measured by shared growth, not just profit</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>What if schools taught this? Or governments governed by it? Could we heal the planet by seeing it as a garden—not a resource to exploit?</strong></p>

<h2 id="gardens-of-possibilities">Gardens of possibilities</h2>

<p>The world today feels like a garden parched by a relentless sun—our systems, once vibrant, are wilting under the weight of extraction, inequality, and disconnection. The shift from financial to relational capital isn’t just an economic choice—it’s a personal and planetary imperative.</p>

<p>This is the garden we must tend—a place where:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Imagination</strong> blooms as we dream of new possibilities, not bound by old constraints</li>
  <li><strong>Autonomy</strong> empowers each of us to act with purpose, not just follow orders</li>
  <li><strong>Relatedness</strong> binds us in trust and collaboration, not competition</li>
  <li><strong>Mastery</strong> lets us refine our skills and wisdom, not just chase profit</li>
</ul>

<p>This isn’t a top-down mandate or a grassroots uprising—it’s a multifaceted momentum:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A child teaching their parent a new way to compost, while the parent shares decades of gardening wisdom</li>
  <li>A CEO learning from employees to redesign supply chains, while the employees gain new perspectives on global impact</li>
  <li>A government funding regenerative projects inspired by ancient First People’s wisdom, while communities gain new resources and recognition</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="your-invitation-to-the-garden">Your invitation to the garden</h2>

<p>Healing begins when we see ourselves as gardeners, not consumers. When we nurture relationships over transactions, wisdom over data, and life over profit. The garden thrives not because of a single hero, but because every seed, every hand, every story plays its part.</p>

<p>You are invited to be a gardener—to see your choices as seeds, your relationships as roots, and your purpose as the soil that nourishes us all. The shift to relational capital isn’t a destination—it’s a practice. A daily choice to tend the garden, to see the world as a living, breathing ecosystem where every act of care ripples outward.</p>

<p><strong>The time is now. The garden awaits. Will you <a href="/get-involved/">join us</a>?</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>David Berigny</name></author><category term="Provocations" /><category term="relationality" /><category term="systems-change" /><category term="regeneration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A garden of relational capital is a place where we can cultivate the seeds of a new economy, one that is based on the principles of relationality, systems change, and regeneration.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/relational-capital-garden.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/relational-capital-garden.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking the Cycle of Trauma Through Transformation</title><link href="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/02/09/breaking-the-cycle-of-trauma-thru-transformation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking the Cycle of Trauma Through Transformation" /><published>2025-02-09T01:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-09T01:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/02/09/breaking-the-cycle-of-trauma-thru-transformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/02/09/breaking-the-cycle-of-trauma-thru-transformation/"><![CDATA[<p>I was born into a world of trauma, though it took me years to understand that. As a kid, I learned the lessons that child abuse teaches: stay alert, stay small, stay ready.
When safety feels like a game of chance, your body learns to play defence first and ask questions later.</p>

<p>But surviving is not the same as healing. And healing is needed for us to re-pattern and transform.</p>

<p>For years, I carried those deep seated patterns everywhere I went, like invisible armour that was getting heavier by the day. I got really good at spotting danger around corners, at keeping people at arm’s length, deflecting praise, denying help, while secretly longing for connection. Throughout my twenties I could easily intellectualise about trauma, but my nervous system was still running emergency drills 24/7.</p>

<p>But transformation happens. For me it took years of deep therapy where I was fortunate enough to have a mentor at the time that covered the costs. Culminating in meeting the abuser in-person and seeing them as a broken human that was unable to re-pattern their own abuse induced trauma. Luckily being able to forgive them in shared tears before they died soon after. Many somatic rituals to re/cognise with body, heart and mind as one. I’d then enlisted the help of shamans and plant medicines and spent a decade integrating the deep wisdom that comes from these journeys of self and the universe. Much reflection and sharing my pain. With family and friends and even with strangers on the train or homeless people on the streets of Sydney as I wandered in deep contemplation as a flaneur of our modern world and that of what is within.</p>

<p>The journey of unwinding those patterns? Messy, uncomfortable and nonlinear, and also, completely worth it.</p>

<p>Healing has meant catching myself in those moments when fear is making my choices for me. It’s meant questioning the logic of harm that was planted not just in my childhood, but in the very ground we all walk on. In the stories we tell and repeat everyday through how we hold ourselves and show up in the world.</p>

<p>It’s meant challenging toxic statements from other men like “toughen up cupcake” or some bro misquoting Darwin with a trope about “survival of the fittest”. I learned to challenge not through the method of physical violence that I was all too familiar with in my youth but through a sense of compassion that they are actually traumatised too.</p>

<p>And even as I continue to this day the slow somatic work to transform these patterns in myself, I’m living in a society that keeps creating new trauma every day. In people, in communities, in the earth itself.</p>

<p>Hurt people hurt people. The hurt carries through into what we create, the systems. The tech. The ways of being, doing and learning. The patterns of trauma continuing. And in this is beauty too. Coming through in our artistic expressions as humans. Coming through our healing journies together, the shadow present because of the light.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/posts/shadows-in-light.jpg" alt="people on top of a hill with light of the sunset behind them and the wide ocean with a small island in the distance" class="blog-image" />
  <figcaption>Fellow Earthians on the healing journey with Yage in Costa Rica 2013</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Every time I have revisited this post to draft and redraft. I have sobbed. Tears shed quietly in my office. Sometimes walking into my garden barefoot to just feel and heal. My partner in life and kids coming in to heal with me. A hug and reassurance to my body that it is going to be okay. This is the real work. It’s the work of feeling, witnessing, and honouring the full weight of our experiences while still choosing to move toward healing and transformation. Part of the collective re-patterning, I believe down to my bones that we so desperately need.</p>

<p>Because healing isn’t just a personal journey. It’s collective. And we’re all on the journey together on Spaceship Earth.</p>

<h2 id="a-world-that-hurts">A world that hurts</h2>

<p>The perpetuating patterns of unresolved trauma means our world is set up in ways that keep hurting people. It’s like we’re stuck in a loop, passing pain from one generation to the next. The patterns continuing to play out in so many aspects of our lives.</p>

<h3 id="our-relationships">Our relationships</h3>

<ul>
  <li>The beatdowns of a voice in your head telling you to “suck it up”, ignore the pain and keep going when you’re hurting</li>
  <li>A parent screaming at their child to confront their fears at a sports game they are playing in because they never got to play</li>
  <li>Partners projecting onto each other in continual cycles of abuse their parents inflicted on each other and them</li>
  <li>Children being bullied at home carrying it through onto the playground and into adulthood and the boardroom</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-daily-grind">The daily grind</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Working jobs that drain our souls because bills need paying with a monopoly money that keeps us trapped in a cycle of debt and conspicuous consumption</li>
  <li>Watching the places we love get torn down for profit or the trees in the parks we love getting destroyed so a road for cars can be built for the “economy”</li>
  <li>Feeling guilty because our “consumer” choices seem to hurt the planet, even when we’re trying our best to be sustainable</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-bigger-picture">The bigger picture</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Communities getting pushed out of their homes by rising costs and the war march of modernity and economic growth</li>
  <li>People being killed to continue the colonialist project and make more rich people richer because while we are all complicit in the system</li>
  <li>Kids learning to dim their light in schools that value tests over creativity</li>
  <li>The constant buzzing of anxiety about climate change, war and collapse</li>
  <li>The exhaustion of trying to keep up with a system that never stops demanding more and more from us and the planet</li>
</ul>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-terra-sky
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/horizons/3-deep-horizons.png')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>In all of this is a paradox of positive systemic change we must navigate.</h2>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<h2 id="through-the-paradoxical-loop">Through the paradoxical loop</h2>

<p>We are all traumatised. Yet we must transform. There’s no time to beat around the bush and hold hands in circles singing kumbaya… right? But like having a splinter in your finger: it hurts, the pain telling us something needs attention. And the longer we ignore it, the more it festers. Yet we keep ignoring it or are just sometimes simply too darn afraid to pull it out.</p>

<h3 id="the-comfort-trap">The comfort trap</h3>

<p>We get used to things being broken. Sometimes it feels easier to adapt to deep pain through repression than to challenge it. That’s how:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Companies normalise burnout as “hustle culture”</li>
  <li>We accept endless scrolling as “staying informed”</li>
  <li>Communities accept pollution as the price of “progress”</li>
  <li>Citizens accept the lesser of two evils when passing a vote</li>
  <li>We accept the status quo because it’s “just the way things are”</li>
  <li>We ignore the pain of our past because it’s “just the way we are”</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-change-paradox">The change paradox</h3>

<p>The catch? Real healing often means disrupting the systems we rely on. It’s scary. It’s uncomfortable. And yet, it’s so fucking necessary.</p>

<p>Trauma creates cycles of adaptation, but adaptation is not always healing. Societies normalise harm to survive it, but this prevents true transformation.</p>

<p>Then there is the cycle of replicating trauma in change-making efforts. Many movements meant to dismantle harmful systems unconsciously recreate them. Through hierarchy, exclusion, urgency culture, and burnout.</p>

<p>Healing is disruptive. And unlearning trauma-conditioned ways of being, thinking and acting can feel threatening because they challenge familiar structures, even when those structures harm us. Even when we believe, misguided or not, that these are the only ways to survive.</p>

<p>Here is where I feel the creative tension of this paradox… systemic trauma is both a barrier and a catalyst. The very conditions that break people down also create the conditions for awakening, resistance, and change.</p>

<h2 id="crafting-something-new">Crafting something new</h2>

<p>But this is where active hope comes in. Like a forest after a fire, new life can grow from old wounds. Active hope is being able to maintain hope in the face on what may seem like insurmountable odds purely because you take action to move through and with it.</p>

<p>And we can pattern this together.</p>

<h3 id="from-survival-to-alive">From survival to alive</h3>

<p>Instead of just getting by in a world that hurts, we can:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Create spaces where we help each other co-regulate to feel safe enough to dream</li>
  <li>Nurture communities of care that share resources instead of hoarding them</li>
  <li>Design for systemic change work that energises rather than depletes</li>
  <li>Learn from and with nature about reciprocity, healing, and regeneration</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="small-steps-big-changes">Small steps, big changes</h3>

<p>Change happens in rings, like a tree growing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Start with creating the conditions for healing circles, where people can be real about their pain</li>
  <li>Connect with those people that are the positive deviants around you that are already doing the work</li>
  <li>Celebrate small wins and learn from setbacks as a community</li>
  <li>Keep showing up, even when it’s messy in whatever way you can</li>
</ul>

<p>Every ring, every circle of care is us collectively growing the tree of transformation. It’s a slow process, but it’s the only way to break the cycle.</p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-terra-sky
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/posts/fractal-spirals.jpg')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>Healing isn't a straight line. It's more like a spiral as we keep coming back to old patterns, but each time with new wisdom.</h2>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<h2 id="the-path-forward">The path forward</h2>

<p>Healing is neurons firing and rewiring together. The relational weaving work of re-storying and re-patterning. Re/cognising the pain. Releasing the pain. Remembering the joy of being alive.</p>

<p>The key is remembering we’re not alone in this work.</p>

<h3 id="what-we-can-do-today">What we can do today</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Notice where we’re hurting and be gentle with ourselves</li>
  <li>Find others who want to craft something better</li>
  <li>Trust that healing ripples out through our relations, even when we can’t see it</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="a-call-to-relationship">A call to relationship</h2>

<p>We’re living in a wounded world, but we’re not powerless. Every time we choose connection over isolation, creativity over consumption, love over fear, cooperation over competition, or healing over repression, we’re helping to break the cycle. Every time we share our stories, listen deeply to each other, or dare to imagine something different, we’re part of the change we know the world needs.</p>

<p>The future we need won’t be built by ignoring our collective trauma - it’ll be crafted from transforming it, together. And that work? It starts with us, right here, right now.</p>

<p>What’s your story? What patterns are you ready to break? What small step will you take today?</p>

<p>Because healing might be hard, but you’re not in it alone. Not anymore.</p>]]></content><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><category term="Transformation" /><category term="Collective Healing" /><category term="Regeneration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An exploration of trauma-informed systemic change]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/trauma-healing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/trauma-healing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Thrutopian Paths and Germinating Radicle Seeds of the Symbiocene</title><link href="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/01/22/introducing-collective-futurecrafting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thrutopian Paths and Germinating Radicle Seeds of the Symbiocene" /><published>2025-01-22T06:20:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T06:20:11+00:00</updated><id>https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/01/22/introducing-collective-futurecrafting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/blog/2025/01/22/introducing-collective-futurecrafting/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re in a phase transition<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> as a species. A liminal space between worlds, beginnings and endings. And we must ask ourselves, given what we sense about this juncture in our history, how must we be? What must we do? What are we preparing to become?</p>

<p>Like mycelia sensing changes in the soil, there’s a deep knowing stirring in our collective body—a recognition that we stand at a threshold of profound transformation. This knowing has been whispering to me, and I sense to many others, through dreams and garden conversations, through data points and pattern re/cognition, through the quiet persistence of life finding new ways to flourish.</p>

<p>I spent a fair amount of time marinating on what to write for this first post as the website births. How to write it, the stories to tell, the empirical research and wide boundary thinking and thinkers to draw on, those that have inspired this work, this craft that has been whispering to me, well, for much of my life. For what I feel is many lifetimes. Feeling through depths of ancestral patterns, journeys with magic chocolate, reflecting on the yarns with friends, local Elders, my dogs and the plants in the garden as I water them. Reflections on the quests I have been on. From the jungles of Mexico and Costa Rica, to Papua New Guinea and Australia.</p>

<p>We are always becoming and all that has been is compost for radicles to emerge in the present moment.</p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-sky-terra
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/posts/garden-image.jpg')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
  <h2>Seeds in the garden of time</h2>
  <p>For the past year, I sat in my backyard garden every Futurecrafting Friday. Being with the enormity of stimuli, sitting with the sense of something that wants to be born.</p>
  <p>Knowing what is spoken, can become. What is felt, can be done.</p> <p>And what is imagined can be crafted.</p>
  
    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<p><br />
And there is a wonderful reimagining happening all around us. Like the fruiting bodies of the mycelium underneath the soil, popping up after the rains. Or how the undergrowth that begins thriving as an old tree dies and opens up the canopy. Initiatives all around the world to reimagine what it means to be citizens, to rewild, to repattern, to reconnect with ourselves, to re/cognise. Whispers in peoples dreams, in conversations in passing, in the quiet hum that is our yearning for deep belonging.</p>

<p>At the same time there is so much upheaval, turmoil, and continuation of trauma while <a href="https://www.planetaryhealthcheck.org/" target="_blank">Spaceship Earth’s vital signs</a> are flashing red. Wars across the world, wars on our psyches, ongoing exploitation of people, of forests, of our Earth. This cannot be ignored as it is in this trauma that lies the <span class="footnote-ref">radicle<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup><span class="footnote-tooltip">A radicle is the first part of a seedling (a growing plant embryo) to emerge from the seed during the process of germination. See footnote for futher context.</span></span> seeds of healing if we are willing to work through it together.</p>

<h2 id="the-edge-of-transformation">The edge of transformation</h2>

<p>As a skeptical optimist looking at all the data points, I think, yes, there is so much beauty emerging from what one might call a “raising of consciousness”. A rising of more wellbeing aligned policies, regenerative practices, circular design, Doughnut Economics, <a href="https://innerdevelopmentgoals.org/" target="_blank">Inner Development Goals</a>, cooperatives, web3 tech, ideas spreading across the nooshphere etc etc. But the question is can it rise <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/dec/28/we-need-dramatic-social-and-technological-changes-is-societal-collapse-inevitable" target="_blank">fast enough</a> to bring about the radical transformation required for our deeply global civilisation to come into right relation with the web of life?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Whether it is to be utopia or oblivion will be a touch-and-go relay race right up to the final moment.”</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Buckminster Fuller</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We are shifting the discussion of what is acceptable and what is not, and a lot of good, positive things are happening. But the question is, will it happen fast enough?”</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Danilo Brozović</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>My more woo-er senses bring me to the belief that this is a cosmic story playing out that we are part of and we are destined to transform. A metamorphosis we must have as a species.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/images/posts/Metamorphosis-2005-Alex-Grey-watermarked.jpg" alt="Alex Grey artwork depicting transformation" class="blog-image" />
  <figcaption>Image credit: <a href="https://www.alexgrey.com/art/nature-field/metamorphosis" target="_blank">Alex Grey</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The path to walk through all this is the one of preparing for the end times as we know it. For it is not a utopian or dystopian path we are on, it is <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/rupert-read/thrutopia-why-neither-dys_b_18372090.html" target="_blank">Thrutopian</a>.</p>

<h2 id="walking-thrutopian-paths">Walking thrutopian paths</h2>

<p>In 2010 while I was a “mature age student” at uni I did a pivotal subject called Utopias &amp; Dystopias (if you’re curious see a <a href="https://www.m3data.me/new-dawns-creative-essay/" target="_blank">creative essay</a> I wrote for this subject). This period brought with it a wide immersion in the utopian and dystopian literature and a hint at the thinking that was to shape the trajectory of my work in the following decade. My professor was Dr Jeremy Walker, someone I admired and who had deeply inspired me. His more <a href="https://epress.lib.uts.edu.au/journals/index.php/mcs/article/view/8813" target="_blank">recent research work</a> on the Atlas Network, a shady web of people and “think-tanks” that colluded to support the No vote in Australia’s recent referendum is noteworthy. It symbolises the current power structures, patterns and institutions that must be composted as we find and craft Thrutopian paths towards what Glen Albrecht calls the <a href="https://symbioscene.com/invitation-to-the-symbiocene/" target="_blank">Symbiocene</a>. An era after the Anthropocene where we are in right relation with the Earth and all her beings.</p>

<p>Like composting itself, transformation requires both breaking down and building up. Over the past several years, I have noticed a deeper shift emerging—a dispersed movement focused on futures that is finding coherence. Not just the theoretical futures of an academic nature, these have increased in recent years as a result of the acknowledgement we have some serious adaption to do. But the lived futures being crafted in community gardens, citizen assemblies, platform coops, Decentralised Autonomous Organisations and Web3 communities,  around kitchen tables, in many spaces and places where people dare to dream differently. A <a href="https://www.wired.com/2008/06/scenius-or-comm/" target="_blank">scenius</a> of people, as Brian Eno calls it, who are bringing new patterns of belonging, of governance, of economy, of culture into being.</p>

<p>Even in the political realms the Overton windows are seemingly shifting to more preferable policy. Of course there is variance based on where on this wonderful planet you are. Writing this at a time where we’ve just had another legit criminal made president of the US, it seems like a stretch to say that the political realms are shifting fast enough.</p>

<p>Where I am located on Spaceship Earth, on the East Coast of the Australian  continent, nothing in my view is radicle enough. Regulatory capture, the ongoing exploitation of people and the Earth, the lack of meaningful action on climate change and we could just go on and on. But I won’t. For it is in the shadows that the light shines brightest. And it is in the shadows that the seeds of transformation are germinating.</p>

<p>We need not wait for politicians, bureaucrats in the Ministry of Futility<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, for the WEFerati<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>, for Elonia Musk, for the current institutions to make the changes we most need for the transformation.</p>

<p>It happens at the edges, in our communities, conversations and yarns. In the small rituals we practice. In the processing of our trauma and the quieter transformations we embrace. In positive deviance, and the small acts of loving kindness, rebellion, active hope and civil disobedience.</p>

<p>This is what creates the conditions for paths to the Symbiocene.</p>

<h2 id="patterns-wanting-to-be-reborn">Patterns wanting to be (re)born</h2>

<p>Sitting in my garden these past several months, watching the interplay of sunlight through leaves and the dance of ecology, something has been chrysalising.</p>

<p>Whispering to me in the quiet moments between thoughts, in the spaces where past and future dance together. Teasing me in my dreams and drawings. It spoke in the language of living systems, in sacred geometries, in the language of both the mystical and the magical.</p>

<p>Every morning when I enter my office and every <span class="footnote-ref">Futurecrafting Friggsday<span class="footnote-tooltip">Futurecrafting Friggsday refers to Friday, named after Frigg, the Norse goddess of foresight - a dedicated day for contemplating and crafting futures. See footnote for further context.</span></span><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> in my garden, I close my eyes and take a deep breath, feeling into the Torus of energy flowing around and through my body, picturing the energy of our Mother Earth pulsating through the mycorrhizal networks beneath me. The energy connecting through the soles of my feet, flowing up through my legs, into my torso, flowing through my arms and into the tips of my fingers, working its way up through the crown of my head, where a golden light shoots out and connects with a golden light coming from the sky.</p>

<p>This ritual isn’t mere metaphor—it’s what one of my Shamanic teachers <a href="https://www.martispiegelman.org/" target="_blank">Marti Spiegelman</a> calls a technology of consciousness, ancient tools for attuning to and participating in the evolution of awareness itself. These technologies, as old as human culture yet eternally renewed, are the original interfaces through which we’ve learned to navigate the subtle architectures of reality.</p>

<p>As Marti teaches, consciousness is always evolving toward higher expressions of abundant life.</p>

<p>Our role, as both vessels and stewards of this evolution, is to become competent practitioners of its organising principles. Through these embodied practices, we’re not just observing the emergence of new possibilities—we’re actively participating in their birth.</p>

<p>These technologies of consciousness form the foundation of Collective Futurecrafting, complementing the context of circles and often preceding our use of digital tools. They are the deep scaffolding through which we sense, integrate, and midwife the patterns wanting to be (re)born while hospicing those that no longer serve.</p>

<h2 id="symbiotic-intelligence-and-serious-play">Symbiotic intelligence and serious play</h2>

<p>While Collective Futurecrafting’s <a href="/about/origins/" target="_blank">origins</a> planted seeds, it’s ever evolving interplay has led to a germination where the radicle has emerged. Not just through human contemplation, rituals, community projects, yarns and yearns but through a dance with the more-than-human world—including our digital tech extensions. Like mycelial networks that connect trees in forests, our neural networks now extend through to our digital networks through photons of light, creating new possibilities for expanding perception and pattern re/cognition. This is what the brilliant metamodern philosopher George Por calls <a href="https://technoshaman.medium.com/from-van-goghs-bedroom-to-ai-whisperers-with-love-e1ec98a1c14b" target="_blank">AI Shamanism</a> and the techno-paleontologist and systems seer Michael Garfield explores in various ways through his new project <a href="https://michaelgarfield.substack.com/p/hotl-01" target="_blank">Humans on the loop</a>. And playing with these tools to better attune to the inner and outer games is essential to the craft.</p>

<p>Playfulness weaves through all of this as a fundamental force of evolution and learning for me. Through my work at <a href="https://tethix.co" target="_blank">Tethix</a> with <a href="https://ialja.com/" target="_blank">Alja Isaković</a>, and through both professional and personal explorations with tools like ChatGPT, Claude, and Midjourney, and the suite of APIs, I’ve experienced how these technological symbionts can amplify our capacity for pattern re/cognition and moral imagination. Not as oracles or answer machines, but more so as conversational partners in our ongoing learning process of becoming.</p>

<p>While misguided use of these tools can lead to a lack of critical thinking, diminishing meta-cognition, echo chambers, and the spread of misinformation, I’ve found that when used with intention, mindfulness and care, they can be powerful allies in our individual and collective sense-making. Something my Tethix cofounder and I have explored in reasonable depth over the past 2 years.</p>

<p>They have not replaced the relationships I have with preexisting lo/hi-tech tools; handwritten journalling, notetaking, whiteboarding and visual sketching. Nor reading books or articles online, listening to podcasts, or surfing the web with the eventual 42 tabs open in my browser. They have extended existing patterns of sense-making, learning, making, doing and being.</p>

<p>As I’ve played with these tools, I’ve noticed how they’ve helped me to see patterns in my thinking, to surface assumptions, to explore new possibilities, to deepen my understanding of complex systems, and to craft new narratives on this loop.</p>

<p>Most powerfully, these tools haven’t just extended my cognition—they’ve become part of my sensory apparatus for perceiving possibility. As Donna Haraway reminds us, we’ve always been cyborgs<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>. From fire and the first stone tools to written language to Large Language Models, technology is entangled in our evolution. What’s different now is our growing capacity and speed through which we can consciously participate in this current phase of becoming.</p>

<p>This technological entanglement isn’t separate from our work of crafting futures—it’s integral to it. We’re learning to use these new tools to map and navigate the possibility spaces of emergence. And I truly believe they’re part of our expanded sensory system for perceiving and participating in the birthing of the Symbiocene.</p>

<details class="accordion">
        <summary class="accordion__trigger">A note on ethical considerations</summary>
        <div class="accordion__content">
          <p>Now there are many ethical considerations we could delve 😉 into when it comes to these technologies. From the extractive nature of the business models themselves, the ecological footprint of the current architechtures and supply chains, to the implications of misguided use on our critical thinking faculties as humans, not to mention questions of intimacy and emotional attachment.</p><p>Much of the work I have been immersed in over the last several years has been action research in these areas and more.</p><p>I don't want to get bogged down on these considerations in this post and will write more on this topic as it specifically relates to Collective Futurecrafting. But the ethical considerations are always present in my mind and heart as I navigate this process of becoming and are a core part of my everyday work in the field of tech ethics.</p><p>For now, I invite you to consider the ethical implications of your own use of these technologies and how they might be shaping your own sense-making and sense-giving.</p>
        </div>
      </details>

<h2 id="the-architecture-of-small-moves">The architecture of small moves</h2>

<p>What has been re/cognised through this dance of human intelligence, of ancestral wisdom, of yarns with First Nations Elders of the Dharawal and Eora Nations, neighbours, colleagues, friends, family, plants and emerging technology, is deceptively simple: small circles of people (that sweet spot between 5 and 7) gathering regularly to listen deeply to their place, to process trauma, to prototype small interventions that might ripple outward, and to share stories and learnings through networks that mirror nature’s own information highways.</p>

<p>Now none of this is new. You can see these patterns explicity in <a href="https://www.sociocracyforall.org/" target="_blank">Sociocracy</a> and <a href="https://www.holacracy.org/" target="_blank">Holocracy</a>. In indigenous governance, in high trust teams and more. And just so many more Earthians finding ways to be and let these patterns work through them. (For a more extensive acknolwedgement see the <a href="/craft/patterns/#pattern-inspiration" target="_blank"> patterns</a> page.)</p>

<p>But within and amidst the expression of these ancestral patterns of communing are <a href="" target="_blank">practices</a> to let them work through us. From the micro to the macro. These might be the somatic technologies of consciousness and ritual practices to embed and embody in daily life. Or the larger rituals of community gatherings and deep listening to the land and the stories of our ancestors on planet Earth. From the playful experimentation with new technologies to the serious play of crafting new narratives and making them real and positively impactful in the communities and ecologies in which we live. I imagine these principles, patterns and practices as a living system that we tend together.</p>

<p>And really it’s called Collective Futurecrafting because it’s not about predicting or controlling the future, but about participating artfully in its emergence as a craft itself. Like gardening, it requires both intention and surrender, both careful tending and trust in life’s inherent creativity and wisdom.</p>

<p>It is an ongoing process of becoming that will evolve. And learnings from this evolution will be shared in the open as I sit and commune with my fellow mission stewards and community crafters. As we pilot the principles, patterns and practices through my local kids school P&amp;C and in the various communities we are all part of. Playing it out as we live it out.</p>

<p>In the words of <a href="https://adriennemareebrown.net/" target="_blank">Adrienne Maree Brown</a></p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-terra-sky
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/assets/images/horizons/3-deep-horizons.png')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>What we practice at the small scale sets the patterns for the whole system.</h2>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>
<p><br />
So, what is it we must practice in the process of becoming and crafting that which is calling us to be in service to the Earth and all her beings?</p>

<h2 id="an-invocation-to-practice-and-craft-together">An invocation to practice and craft together</h2>

<p>And so this emerges - both declaration and invocation. Gestated through garden contemplations, plant medicine teachings, and yarns that weave across time with Elders, ancestors, and friends. Through dances with digital minds that are mirroring back our own becoming.</p>

<p>Because the Thrutopian path to the Symbiocene is not the straight lines of industrial thinking. It meanders like water finding its way, following the contours of emergence, shaped by the landscape of our relationsips, collective learning and unlearning. It’s a journey through the territories of trust, through fields of failure and forests of feedback, guided by love for and with the living world.</p>

<p>This is an invocation into praxis:</p>

<ul>
  <li>To gather in circles in your place, letting locality and seasonality guide your rhythm</li>
  <li>To experiment with regenerative rituals that rewire patterns of relating</li>
  <li>To share your learnings through stories that spiral outward (#CollectiveFuturecrafting)</li>
  <li>To participate in crafting new narratives that positively contribute to our species’ metamorphosis</li>
</ul>

<p>For the future isn’t a destination we arrive at, but a shared story we craft together.</p>

<p>The Thrutopian path to the Symbiocene begins here, in this eternal moment pregnant with possibility. The space between where what’s dying feeds what’s being born.</p>

<p>Will you <a href="/get-involved">craft with us</a>?</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Phase transition refers to a fundamental change in a system’s state, like water turning to steam. In social systems, it describes periods of profound transformation where old patterns break down and new ones emerge. See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phase_transition" target="_blank">Wikipedia</a> for more. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>A radicle is the part of a plant embryo that develops into the primary root. For deeper inspiration, see <a href="https://radiclecivics.cc/" target="_blank">Radicle Civics</a>, an initiative from <a href="https://darkmatterlabs.org/" target="_blank">Dark Matter Labs</a> that explores new forms of civic governance. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>The Ministry of Futility is a fictional institution that represents the bureaucratic inertia and systemic failures that often prevent meaningful change. It’s a nod to the challenges of navigating complex systems and the need for new approaches to governance and decision-making. I created a interactive fiction game called <a href="https://m3data.github.io/Ministry-of-Futility-Game/" target="_blank">The Ministry of Futility</a> as a way to explore these themes. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>WEFerati is a colloquial term referring to the elite attendees and proponents of the World Economic Forum’s vision for the future. It’s a playful nod to the power dynamics and techno-optimism often associated with the Davos crowd and their influence on global policy. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Futurecrafting Friggsday refers to Friday, named after Frigg, or Freya, the Norse goddess of foresight - a dedicated day for contemplating and crafting futures. I have ritualised this day for the past year and similar to Fridays for Future, it is a day to contemplate and craft the futures we want to see. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>Donna Haraway’s concept of the cyborg, introduced in her 1985 “Cyborg Manifesto,” suggests that humans have always been hybrid beings, constantly integrating tools and technology into our ways of being. This challenges the idea of ‘pure’ nature and suggests that our technological extensions are part of our evolution as a species. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><category term="Introduction" /><category term="phase-transition" /><category term="collective-intelligence" /><category term="symbiocene" /><category term="thrutopia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re in a phase transition1 as a species. A liminal space between worlds, beginnings and endings. And we must ask ourselves, given what we sense about this juncture in our history, how must we be? What must we do? What are we preparing to become? Phase transition refers to a fundamental change in a system’s state, like water turning to steam. In social systems, it describes periods of profound transformation where old patterns break down and new ones emerge. See Wikipedia for more. &#8617;]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/intro.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://collectivefuturecrafting.net/assets/images/posts/intro.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>