<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-08T21:25:26+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Collective Futurecrafting</title><subtitle>The future is not written. It is crafted.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Introducing Collective Futurecrafting: A Way Thru to the Symbiocene</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/theory/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Collective Futurecrafting: A Way Thru to the Symbiocene" /><published>2025-01-08T17:20:11+11:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T17:20:11+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/theory/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/theory/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting.html"><![CDATA[<p>We’re in a phase transition as a species. A liminal space between worlds, beginnings and endings. And we must ask ourselves, given what we sense about this juncture in our history, how must we be? What must we do? What are we preparing to become?</p>

<p>I spent a fair amount of time marinating on what to write for this first post. How to write it, the stories to tell, the empirical research and wide boundary thinking and thinkers to draw on, those that have inspired this work, this craft that has been whispering to me, well, for much of my life. For what I feel is many lifetimes. Feeling through depths of patterns, nibbling on some magic chocolate, reflecting on the yarns with friends, local Elders, my dogs and the plants in the garden as I water them. Reflections on the quests I have been on. From the jungles of Mexico and Costa Rica, to Papua New Guinea and Australia.</p>

<p>I sat, with the the enormity of feelings every Futurecrafting Friggsday, of what wants to be born. Knowing what is spoken, can become. What is felt, can be done. And what is imagined can be crafted.</p>

<p>In the words of Adrienne Maree Brown:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“What we practice at the small scale sets the patterns for the whole system.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, what is it we must practice in the process of becoming and crafting our futures? What is the craft that is calling us to be in service to the Earth and all her beings?</p>

<p>To be continued in the next commit…</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><category term="Introduction" /><category term="Theory" /><category term="collective action" /><category term="social innovation" /><category term="indigenous wisdom" /><category term="systems thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re in a phase transition as a species. A liminal space between worlds, beginnings and endings. And we must ask ourselves, given what we sense about this juncture in our history, how must we be? What must we do? What are we preparing to become?]]></summary></entry></feed>