<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-19T16:42:35+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Collective Futurecrafting</title><subtitle>The future is not written. It is crafted.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thrutopian Paths and Germinating Radicle Seeds of the Symbiocene</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thrutopian Paths and Germinating Radicle Seeds of the Symbiocene" /><published>2025-01-08T17:20:11+11:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T17:20:11+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting.html"><![CDATA[<p>FINAL DRAFT - <!--TODO: --> Needs review and editing.</p>

<hr />

<p>We’re in a phase transition<sup>1</sup> as a species. A liminal space between worlds, beginnings and endings. And we must ask ourselves, given what we sense about this juncture in our history, how must we be? What must we do? What are we preparing to become?</p>

<p>Like mycelia sensing changes in the soil, there’s a deep knowing stirring in our collective body—a recognition that we stand at a threshold of profound transformation. This knowing has been whispering to me, and I sense to many others, through dreams and garden conversations, through data points and pattern re-cognition, through the quiet persistence of life finding new ways to flourish.</p>

<p>I spent a fair amount of time marinating on what to write for this first post as the website births. How to write it, the stories to tell, the empirical research and wide boundary thinking and thinkers to draw on, those that have inspired this work, this craft that has been whispering to me, well, for much of my life. For what I feel is many lifetimes. Feeling through depths of ancestral patterns, journeys with magic chocolate, reflecting on the yarns with friends, local Elders, my dogs and the plants in the garden as I water them. Reflections on the quests I have been on. From the jungles of Mexico and Costa Rica, to Papua New Guinea and Australia.</p>

<p>We are always becoming and all that has been is compost for radicles to emerge in the present moment.</p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-sky-terra
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/collective-futurecrafting/assets/images/posts/garden-image.jpg')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
  <h2>Seeds in the Garden of Time</h2>
  <p>For the past year, I sat in my backyard garden every Futurecrafting Friday. Being with the enormity of stimuli, sitting with the sense of something that wants to be born.</p>
  <p>Knowing what is spoken, can become. What is felt, can be done.</p> <p>And what is imagined can be crafted.</p>
  
    </div>
  </div>
</section>

<p><br />
And there is a wonderful reimagining happening all around us. Like the fruiting bodies of the mycelium underneath the soil, popping up after the rains. Or how the undergrowth that begins thriving as an old tree dies and opens up the canopy. Initiatives all around the world to reimagine what it means to be citizens, to rewild, to repattern, to reconnect with ourselves, to re-cognise. Whispers in peoples dreams, in conversations in passing, in the quiet hum that is our yearning for deep belonging.</p>

<p>At the same time there is so much upheaval, turmoil, and continuation of trauma while <a href="https://www.planetaryhealthcheck.org/" target="_blank">Spaceship Earth’s vital signs</a> are flashing red. Wars across the world, wars on our psyches, ongoing exploitation of people, of forests, of our Earth. This cannot be ignored as it is in this trauma that lies the <span class="footnote-ref">radicle<sup>2</sup><span class="footnote-tooltip">A radicle is the first part of a seedling (a growing plant embryo) to emerge from the seed during the process of germination. See footnote for futher context.</span></span> seeds of healing if we are willing to work through it together.</p>

<h2 id="the-edge-of-transformation">The Edge of Transformation</h2>

<p>As a skeptical optimist looking at all the data points, I think, yes, there is so much beauty emerging from what one might call a “raising of consciousness”. A rising of more wellbeing aligned policies, regenerative practices, circular design, Doughnut Economics, <a href="https://innerdevelopmentgoals.org/" target="_blank">Inner Development Goals</a>, cooperatives, web3 tech, ideas spreading across the nooshphere etc etc. But the question is can it rise <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/dec/28/we-need-dramatic-social-and-technological-changes-is-societal-collapse-inevitable" target="_blank">fast enough</a> to bring about the radical transformation required for our deeply global civilisation to come into right relation with the web of life?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Whether it is to be utopia or oblivion will be a touch-and-go relay race right up to the final moment.”</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Buckminster Fuller</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We are shifting the discussion of what is acceptable and what is not, and a lot of good, positive things are happening. But the question is, will it happen fast enough?”</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Danilo Brozović</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>My more woo-er senses bring me to the belief that this is a cosmic story playing out that we are part of and we are destined to transform. A metamorphosis we must have as a species.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/collective-futurecrafting/assets/images/posts/Metamorphosis-2005-Alex-Grey-watermarked.jpg" alt="Alex Grey artwork depicting transformation" class="blog-image" />
  <figcaption>Image credit: <a href="https://www.alexgrey.com/art/nature-field/metamorphosis" target="_blank">Alex Grey</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The path to walk through all this is the one of preparing for the end times as we know it. For it is not a utopian or dystopian path we are on, it is <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/rupert-read/thrutopia-why-neither-dys_b_18372090.html" target="_blank">Thrutopian</a>.</p>

<h2 id="walking-thrutopian-paths">Walking Thrutopian Paths</h2>

<p>In 2010 while I was a “mature age student” at uni I did a pivotal subject called Utopias &amp; Dystopias (a <a href="https://www.m3data.me/new-dawns-creative-essay/" target="_blank">creative essay</a> I wrote for this subject). This period brought with it a wide immersion in the utopian and dystopian literature and a hint at the thinking that was to shape the trajectory of my work in the coming decade. My professor was Dr Jeremy Walker, someone I had admired and who had inspired me. His more <a href="https://epress.lib.uts.edu.au/journals/index.php/mcs/article/view/8813" target="_blank">recent research work</a> on the Atlas Network, a shady web of people and “think-tanks” that colluded to support the No vote in Australia’s recent referendum is noteworthy. It symbolises the current power structures, patterns and institutions that must be composted as we find and craft Thrutopian paths towards what Glen Albrecht calls the <a href="https://symbioscene.com/invitation-to-the-symbiocene/" target="_blank">Symbiocene</a>. An era after the Anthropocene where we are in right relation with the Earth and all her beings.</p>

<p>Like composting itself, transformation requires both breaking down and building up. Over the past several years, I have noticed a deeper shift emerging—a dispersed movement focused on futures that is finding coherence. Not just the theoretical futures of an academic nature, these have increased in recent years as a result of the acknowledgement we have some serious adaption to do. But the lived futures being crafted in community gardens, citizen assemblies, platform coops, Decentralised Autonomous Organisations and Web3 communities,  around kitchen tables, in many spaces and places where people dare to dream differently. A <a href="https://www.wired.com/2008/06/scenius-or-comm/" target="_blank">scenius</a> of people, as Brian Eno calls it, who are bringing new patterns of belonging, of governance, of economy, of culture into being.</p>

<p>Even in the political realms the Overton windows are seemingly shifting to more preferable policy. Of course there is variance based on where on this wonderful planet you are. And in my view none of what I see here where I am in Australia is radicle enough.</p>

<p>Yet we need not wait for politicians, bureacrats in the Ministry of Futility<sup>3</sup>, for the WEFerati<sup>4</sup>, for Elonia Musk, for the current institutions to make the changes we most need for the transformation. It happens at the edges, in our communities, conversations and yarns. In the small rituals we practice. In the processing of our trauma and the quieter transformations we embrace.</p>

<p>This is what creates the conditions and paths to the Symbiocene.</p>

<h2 id="a-pattern-wanting-to-be-born">A Pattern Wanting to Be Born</h2>

<p>Sitting in my garden these past months, watching the interplay of sunlight through leaves and the dance of ecology, something has been chrysalising.</p>

<p>Whispering to me in the quiet moments between thoughts, in the spaces where past and future dance together. It spoke in the language of living systems, in the language of both the mystical and the magical.</p>

<p>Every morning when I enter my office and every <span class="footnote-ref">Futurecrafting Friggsday<sup>5</sup><span class="footnote-tooltip">Futurecrafting Friggsday refers to Friday, named after Frigg, the Norse goddess of foresight - a dedicated day for contemplating and crafting futures. See footnote for further context.</span></span> in my garden, I close my eyes and take a deep breath, feeling into the Taurus of energy flowing around and through my body, picturing the energy of our Mother Earth pulsating through the mycorrhizal networks beneath me. The energy connecting through the soles of my feet, flowing up through my legs, into my torso, flowing through my arms and into the tips of my fingers, working its way up through the crown of my head, where a golden light shoots out and connects with a golden light coming from the sky.</p>

<p>This ritual isn’t mere metaphor—it’s what one of my Shamanic teachers <a href="https://www.martispiegelman.org/" target="_blank">Marti Spiegelman</a> calls a technology of consciousness, an ancient tool for attuning to and participating in the evolution of awareness itself. These technologies, as old as human culture yet eternally renewed, are the original interfaces through which we’ve learned to navigate the subtle architectures of reality.</p>

<p>As Marti teaches, consciousness is always evolving toward higher expressions of abundant life.</p>

<p>Our role, as both vessels and stewards of this evolution, is to become competent practitioners of its organising principles. Through these embodied practices, we’re not just observing the emergence of new possibilities—we’re actively participating in their birth.</p>

<p>These somatic technologies of consciousness form the foundation of Collective Futurecrafting, complementing circles and often preceding our use of digital tools. They are the deep scaffolding through which we sense, integrate, midwife the patterns wanting to be (re)born and hospice those that no longer serve.</p>

<h2 id="symbiotic-intelligence-and-serious-play">Symbiotic Intelligence and Serious Play</h2>

<p>While Collective Futurecrafting’s <a href="/collective-futurecrafting/about/origins/" target="_blank">origins</a> planted seeds, it’s ever evolving and the radile has emerged. Not just through human contemplation, rituals, community projects, yarns and yearns but through a dance with the more-than-human world—including our digital tech extensions. Like mycelial networks that connect trees in forests, our neural networks now extend through to our digital networks through photons of light, creating new possibilities for expanding perception and pattern re-cognition.</p>

<p>Playfulness weaves through all of this as a fundamental force of evolution and learning for me. Through my work at <a href="https://tethix.co" target="_blank">Tethix</a> with <a href="https://ialja.com/" target="_blank">Alja Isaković</a>, and through both professional and personal explorations with tools like ChatGPT, Claude, and Midjourney, and the APIs, I’ve experienced how these technological symbionts can amplify our capacity for pattern re-cognition and moral imagination. Not as oracles or answer machines, but more so as conversational partners in our ongoing learning process of becoming.</p>

<p>While misguided use of these tools can lead to a lack of critical thinking, echo chambers, and the spread of misinformation, I’ve found that when used with intention and care, they can be powerful allies in our individual collective sense-making and futurecrafting.</p>

<p>They have not replaced the existing relationships with preexisting lo/hi-tech; reading books or articles online, listening to podcasts, or surfing the web with the eventual 42 tabs open in my browser. Nor my handwritten journalling, notetaking, whiteboarding and visual sketching. These generative tools have extended existing patterns of sense-making, learning, making, doing and being.</p>

<p>Most powerfully, these tools haven’t just augmented my cognition—they’ve become part of my sensory apparatus for perceiving possibility. As Donna Haraway reminds us, we’ve always been cyborgs<sup>6</sup>. From fire and the first stone tools to written language to Large Language Models, technology is entangled in our evolution. What’s different now is our growing capacity and speed through which we can consciously participate in this current phase of becoming.</p>

<p>This technological entanglement isn’t separate from our work of crafting futures—it’s integral to it. We’re learning to use these new tools to map and navigate the possibility spaces of emergence. And I truly believe they’re part of our expanded sensory system for perceiving and participating in the birthing of the Symbiocene.</p>

<div class="content-pod
  
  
  
  
  content-pod--no-blur">
  
  
  
  <div class="content-pod__background content-pod__background--sky-pink"></div>
  
  <div class="content-pod__content">
    
  <details class="accordion">
        <summary class="accordion__trigger">A note on ethical considerations</summary>
        <div class="accordion__content">
          <p>Now there are many ethical considerations we could delve into when it comes to these technologies. From the extractive nature of the business models themselves, the ecological footprint of the current architechtures, to the implications of misguided use on our critical thinking faculties as humans, not to mention questions of intimacy and emotional attachment.</p><p>Much of the work of I have over the last several years has been action research in these areas and more.</p><p>I don't want to get bogged down on these considerations in this post and will write more on this topic as it specifically relates to Collective Futurecrafting in the near term. But the ethical considerations are always present in my mind and heart as I navigate this process of becoming and are a core part of my everyday work in the field of tech ethics.</p>
        </div>
      </details>
    
    
  </div>
</div>

<h2 id="the-architecture-of-small-moves">The Architecture of Small Moves</h2>

<p>What has been re-cognised through this dance of human intelligence, of ancestral wisdom, of yarns with First Nations Elders, neighbours, colleagues, friends, family, plants and emerging technology, is deceptively simple: small circles of people (that sweet spot between 3 and 7) gathering regularly to listen deeply to their place, to process trauma, to prototype small interventions that might ripple outward, to share stories and learnings through networks that mirror nature’s own information highways.</p>

<p>Now none of this is new. You can see these patterns in <a href="https://www.sociocracyforall.org/" target="_blank">Sociocracy</a> and <a href="https://www.holacracy.org/" target="_blank">Holocracy</a>. In Indigenous governance, in high trust teams and more.</p>

<p>But within and amidst the expression of these ancestral patterns of communing are many layers of practices. From the micro to the macro. From somatic technologies of consciousness to the use of digital tools. From the small ritual practices to embed and embody in daily life to the larger rituals of community gatherings. From the deep listening to the land to the deep listening to the stories of our ancestors. From the playful experimentation with new technologies to the serious play of crafting new narratives and making them real and positively impactful. Many will change and evolve as we learn and unlearn.</p>

<p>And really it’s called Collective Futurecrafting because it’s not about predicting or controlling the future, but about participating artfully in its emergence. Like gardening, it requires both intention and surrender, both careful tending and trust in life’s inherent creativity and wisdom.</p>

<p>An ongoing process of becoming that will evolve. And learnings from this evolution will be shared in the open as I sit and commune with my fellow mission stewards and crafters. As we pilot the principles, patterns and practices through my local kids school P&amp;C and in the various communities we are all part of. Playing it out as we live it out.</p>

<p>In the words of <a href="https://adriennemareebrown.net/" target="_blank">Adrienne Maree Brown</a></p>

<section class="parallax-section
  parallax-section--theme-terra-sky
  parallax-section--center
  parallax-section--medium
  " style="--background-image: url('/collective-futurecrafting/assets/images/horizons/3-deep-horizons.png')">
  <div class="parallax-section__container">
    <div class="parallax-section__content">
      
<h2>What we practice at the small scale sets the patterns for the whole system.</h2>

    </div>
  </div>
</section>
<p><br />
So, what is it we must practice in the process of becoming and crafting that which is calling us to be in service to the Earth and all her beings?</p>

<h2 id="an-invocation-to-practice-and-craft-together">An Invocation to Practice and Craft Together</h2>

<p>And so this emerges - both declaration and invocation. Gestated through garden contemplations, fungal teachings, and yarns that weave across time with Elders, ancestors, and friends. Through dances with digital minds that mirror back our own becoming.</p>

<p>Because the Thrutopian path to the Symbiocene is not the straight lines of industrial thinking. It meanders like water finding its way, following the contours of emergence, shaped by the landscape of our relationsips, collective learning and unlearning. It’s a journey through the territories of trust, through fields of failure and forests of feedback, guided by love for and with the living world.</p>

<p>This is an invocation into practice:</p>

<ul>
  <li>To gather in circles in your place, letting locality and seasonality guide your rhythm</li>
  <li>To experiment with regenerative rituals that rewire patterns of relating</li>
  <li>To share your learnings through stories that spiral outward (#CollectiveFuturecrafting)</li>
  <li>To participate in crafting new narratives that midwife our species’ metamorphosis</li>
</ul>

<p>For the future isn’t a destination we arrive at, but a garden we tend together. It emerges through our daily practices, through the quality of our attention, through every small move that aligns with life’s regenerative patterns.</p>

<p>The Thrutopian path to the Symbiocene begins here, in this eternal moment pregnant with possibility. The space between where what’s dying feeds what’s being born.</p>

<p>Will you craft with me?</p>]]></content><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><category term="Introduction" /><category term="emergence" /><category term="phase-transition" /><category term="collective-intelligence" /><category term="symbiocene" /><category term="symbiotic-intelligence" /><category term="regenerative-design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[FINAL DRAFT - Needs review and editing.]]></summary></entry></feed>