<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-08T18:54:26+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Collective Futurecrafting</title><subtitle>The future is not written. It is crafted.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Introducing Collective Futurecrafting: A Way Thru to the Symbiocene</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/theory/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Collective Futurecrafting: A Way Thru to the Symbiocene" /><published>2025-01-08T17:20:11+11:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T17:20:11+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/theory/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/collective-futurecrafting/introduction/theory/2025/01/08/introducing-collective-futurecrafting.html"><![CDATA[<p>In a world facing unprecedented challenges, from climate change to social fragmentation, we need new ways of coming together to craft better futures. But perhaps “new” isn’t quite the right word. What we need is a remembering—a return to ancient wisdom combined with modern innovations in social coordination.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-circles">The Power of Circles</h2>

<p>Before treaties and territories, before parliaments and protocols, humans gathered in circles. Around fires that held back the dark, beneath stars that mapped our stories, we sat together—listening, relating, sharing, dreaming of what was and what might be.</p>

<p>These circles were our first:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Universities of collective learning</li>
  <li>Governments of mutual care</li>
  <li>Theaters of shared imagination</li>
</ul>

<p>Today, as our world strains under the weight of interwoven crises, these ancient patterns of relating call to us again.</p>

<h2 id="why-collective-futurecrafting">Why Collective Futurecrafting?</h2>

<p>Collective Futurecrafting (CF) emerged from a simple question: How might we create conditions for communities to dream and build flourishing futures together?</p>

<p>The answer led us to develop a framework that:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Starts Small</strong>: Working with groups of 3-7 people in local contexts</li>
  <li><strong>Builds Trust</strong>: Creating space for authentic relationship-building</li>
  <li><strong>Enables Action</strong>: Supporting concrete steps toward better futures</li>
  <li><strong>Scales Organically</strong>: Connecting circles into larger networks of change</li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The future is not something we enter. The future is something we create.” 
— Leonard I. Sweet</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-three-pillars">The Three Pillars</h2>

<h3 id="1-relational-trust">1. Relational Trust</h3>

<p>At the heart of CF lies the understanding that all lasting change grows from trust. Through regular gatherings and shared practices, circles build the relational foundation needed for meaningful collaboration.</p>

<h3 id="2-practical-action">2. Practical Action</h3>

<p>Ideas without action remain dreams. Each circle engages in “perpetual pilots”—small experiments that test possibilities and generate learning. These might include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Community gardens</li>
  <li>Local energy initiatives</li>
  <li>Cultural revival projects</li>
  <li>Educational innovations</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="3-systemic-impact">3. Systemic Impact</h3>

<p>While each circle operates locally, they connect through Community Learning and Action Networks (CLANs) to share:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Stories of success and failure</li>
  <li>Resources and knowledge</li>
  <li>Support and inspiration</li>
  <li>Collaborative opportunities</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h2>

<p>Ready to begin your Collective Futurecrafting journey? Here are three ways to engage:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Join a Circle</strong>: Find an existing circle in your area</li>
  <li><strong>Start a Circle</strong>: Gather a small group and begin your own</li>
  <li><strong>Learn More</strong>: Explore our resources and principles</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-road-ahead">The Road Ahead</h2>

<p>This is just the beginning. As more circles form and connect, we’re creating a living network of people working together to craft futures worthy of our children’s children.</p>

<p>In the words of Adrienne Maree Brown:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“What we practice at the small scale sets the patterns for the whole system.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Let’s practice together.</p>

<h2 id="join-the-movement">Join the Movement</h2>

<p>Ready to be part of this journey? Visit our <a href="/get-involved">Get Involved</a> page to learn how you can start or join a Futurecrafting Circle in your community.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Mathew Mytka</name></author><category term="Introduction" /><category term="Theory" /><category term="collective action" /><category term="social innovation" /><category term="indigenous wisdom" /><category term="systems thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a world facing unprecedented challenges, from climate change to social fragmentation, we need new ways of coming together to craft better futures. But perhaps “new” isn’t quite the right word. What we need is a remembering—a return to ancient wisdom combined with modern innovations in social coordination.]]></summary></entry></feed>